Guide to the Stanford War Records SC0019
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford war records
1917-1945
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Duniway, C. A. (Clyde Augustus)
McDowell, John E.
SC0019
14.25 Linear Feet (30 boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
These records were first given to Stanford University Libraries and then moved to the Hoover Library in 1941. In 1964 they were returned to the Stanford Libraries to become part of the Stanford University Archives.
Custodial History note
Collected by John E. McDowell and Dr. C. A. Duniway, with additions from other sources.
Information about Access
Materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents Note:
These records pertain to Stanford University faculty and student participation in World Wars I and II. Included are papers regarding the establishment of ambulance units; personal narratives of servicemen and correspondence with those in the service; drafts of a Stanford war history by Dr. C. A. Duniway; records of each Stanford participant in the First World War; records regarding women in war work, the Student Army Training Corps, civil defense, and war courses; and photographs and memorabilia.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in three series. The records in Series 1 were collected during 1918-1919 by John E. McDowell, Alumni Secretary, with the assistance of Prof. Edgar E. Robinson. Mr. McDowell was particularly active in corresponding with military personnel. A Committee on War Information was to prepare a "War History of Stanford" from these materials, but nothing came of this effort. In 1936 interest in the war records was revived with the construction of Memorial Hall on the Stanford campus. Dr. C. A. Duniway, former professor of history, engaged in bringing the war records up to date; his collected materials make up Series 2. Although Prof. Duniway prepared a draft of Stanford's war history, it was never published. Series 3 consists of materials from varied sources pertaining to the campus war effort and Stanford personnel in the services during World War II.
Duniway, C. A. (Clyde Augustus); McDowell, John E.
- World War I Subject Files, 1917-1919
  - Ambulance Units. First Stanford Unit, organized Feb. 2, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ambulance Units. Second Stanford Unit, organized April 25, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ambulance Units. Third Stanford Unit (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ambulance Units. Fourth Stanford Unit (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ambulance Units. Fifth Stanford Unit. Italian Ambulance Unit, American Red Cross (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ambulance Units. General literature (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American University Union in Europe Registers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Civil Service. California State Civil Service Commission Announcements (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Civil Service. California State Civil Service Commission Announcements. Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Public Information, Washington, D.C. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Draft (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Engineer enlisted reserve corps. Aeronautical engineers, 472D engineers (Signal Corps) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Faculty War Service Departmental Record (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Faculty War Service, Lists and General matters (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - U. S. Food Administration correspondence, bulletins, etc. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - U. S. Food Administration, food conservation notes (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - U. S. Food Administration. Herbert Clark Hoover. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - U. S. Fuel Administration. Publications and releases. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - U. S. Food Administration Speeches of Dr. Ray Lyman Wilbur (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Liberty Loan Campaign - Third (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Marine Corps Reserve. Marine Reserve Flying Corps (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Medical Enlisted Reserve Corps (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Naval Reserve Flying Corps. Coast Defense Reserve. Engineer's and Technicians' jobs (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Officers' Training School (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Officers' Training School (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Officers' Training School (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Personal narratives of Stanford servicemen (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Personal narratives (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Birge Clark, "World War I Memoirs" (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Personnel (periodical). U. S. Adjutant General Committee on Classification of Personnel in the Army (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Radio Instruction (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - ROTC 2nd Presidio Camp (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Stanford Women's Unit (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Student Army Training Corps (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - War History, blank forms (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - War History, appeals for data (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - War History, correspondence and exemplary materials - other universities (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - War History, survey of materials on file, 1908-04 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - War History, June 1, 1918 report and preliminary summary (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - War History, Aug. 10, 1918 summary of work; Sept. 24, 1918 supplementary report (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - War History, Aug. 15, 1919 report of E. E. Robinson (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - War History, Ambulance Units, list (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - War History, Civilian service, list (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - War History, "History of Stanford in the Great War," by E. E. Robinson (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - War History, decorated, list (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - War History, died in service, list (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - War History, enlisted Medical Reserve Corps (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - War History, Faculty, Civilian-military (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - War History, foreign military service (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - War History, misc. lists and registers (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - War History, Red Cross in uniform (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - War History, wounded (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - War Service Memorial Committee (committee of 50). Minutes, suggestions, news (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - War History, main military list (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - War History, Stanford School of Nurses (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - War History, U. S. Base Hospital #30 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - War History, U. S. Navy Base Hospital (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - War History, Women in Service (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - War History, YMCA (in uniform) (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - War Service Credit (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Women in war work (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Committee on War Information-Organization and Membership (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Committee on War Information-Meeting, Feb. 28, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Committee on War Information-Meeting, Mar. 7, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Committee on War Information-Meeting, Mar. 14, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Committee on War Information-Meeting, Apr. 4, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Committee on War Information-Meeting, Apr. 11, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Committee on War Information-Correspondence, Universities’ War Work (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Committee on War Information-Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - War Service Memorial Fund (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - War Service Memorial Fund (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Women – position in war work (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Women – position in war work (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - YMCA (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Alan Nichols, copies of letters from France, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Alan Nichols, copies of letters from France, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - War Memorial, World War I (General Secretary’s Office) (Box 5, Folder 77)
- World War I Materials Collected by Dr. C. A. Duniway, 1937-1938
  - American Field Service in France (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Camp Fremont (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Stanford Illustrated Review concerning Stanford in the war (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Clippings concerning Stanford in the war (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Duniway, "War History of Stanford" (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Memorial Building (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Military Training Committee (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Misc. printed items (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Stanford Belgian Relief (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Stanford School of Nursing War histories (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Stanford war history chronology (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Stanford war records, index of material, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Stanford YMCA (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Student Army Training Corp. War issues course (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - War History, fraternities (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - War History, sororities (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: A-An (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ao-Az (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ba (1 of 2) (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ba (2 of 2) (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Be-Ben (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ben-Bi (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Bi-Bo (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Br-Broo (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Brow-Bul (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Bun-By (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Cadw-Carl (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Carr-Cl (1 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Carr-Cl (2 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Cl-Cod (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Coe-Cov (1 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Coe-Cov (2 of 2) (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Cow-Cron (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Croo-Cy (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: D-Daz (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: De-Dod (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Doe-Dr (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Dr-Dy (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ea-En (Box 9, Folder 116)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: En-Fal (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Fan-Fi (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Fl-Fra (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Fre-Ga (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ge-Gl (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Go-Gr (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Gu-Hall (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Has-Hel (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Halm-Hart (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Hen-Hoe (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Hen-Hoe (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Hos-Hu (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Hul-Ja (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Je-Jones, N. (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: J (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: K-Key (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ki-Kle (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Kli-Ky (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: L-Lar (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Las-Le (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Li-Ly (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: M-MacI (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: MacI-MacD (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: MacR-Math (Box 14, Folder 140)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Mat-Mil (Box 14, Folder 141)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Min-More (Box 14, Folder 142)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Morg-Murp (Box 14, Folder 143)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Murr-Net (Box 14, Folder 144)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Neu-Ny (Box 14, Folder 145)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: O-Or (Box 14, Folder 146)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Os-Par (Box 15, Folder 147)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Part-Pem (Box 15, Folder 148)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Pen-Pl (Box 15, Folder 149)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Po-Pz (Box 15, Folder 150)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Q (Box 15, Folder 151)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Ra-Re (Box 15, Folder 152)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Rho-Robi (Box 16, Folder 153)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Robl-Ross (Box 16, Folder 154)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Roth-San (Box 16, Folder 155)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Sar-Schn (Box 16, Folder 156)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Scho-Sem (Box 16, Folder 157)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Seo-Sho (Box 16, Folder 158)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Shr-Si (Box 16, Folder 159)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Sk-Smith, H. (Box 17, Folder 160)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Smith, H.-Spa (Box 17, Folder 161)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Spe-Sta (Box 17, Folder 162)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Stea-Stey (Box 17, Folder 163)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Stu-Sty (Box 17, Folder 164)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: T-Te (Box 17, Folder 165)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Th-Ti (Box 17, Folder 166)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: To-Ty (Box 18, Folder 167)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: U-V (Box 18, Folder 168)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: W-Walk (Box 18, Folder 169)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Wal-War (Box 18, Folder 170)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Wash-Well (Box 18, Folder 171)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Wells-Wilc (Box 18, Folder 172)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Wild-Will (Box 18, Folder 173)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Wils-Win (Box 19, Folder 174)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Wir-Wy (Box 19, Folder 175)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: X-Z (Box 19, Folder 176)
  - Alumni Military Service List (1 of 2) (Box 19, Folder 177)
  - Alumni Military Service List (2 of 2) (Box 19, Folder 178)
  - Service with Allies (Box 19, Folder 178)
  - Faculty Civilian Service Rosters (Box 19, Folder 179)
  - Faculty Civilian Service Records (Full-Time) (Box 20, Folder 180)
  - Faculty Civilian Service Records (Part-Time) (Box 20, Folder 181)
  - Faculty War Service Department Reports (Box 20, Folder 182)
  - Faculty War Records: A-F (Box 20, Folder 183)
  - Faculty War Records: G-W (Box 20, Folder 184)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service)-biographical sketches, (1 of 3) (Box 20, Folder 185)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service)-biographical sketches, (2 of 3) (Box 20, Folder 186)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service)-biographical sketches, (3 of 3) (Box 21, Folder 187)
  - Photographs of those who died in service (Box 21, Folder 188)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service)-Files, A-G (Box 21, Folder 189)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service)-Files, H-L (Box 21, Folder 190)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service)-Files, M-R (Box 21, Folder 191)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service)-Files, S-Z (Box 21, Folder 192)
  - The Story of the First Flag [book], 4 copies (Box 22)
  - Photo album, Ambulance Units in the Balkans (Box 22)
  - Box of plates used in printing pictures of servicemen (Box 23)
- World War II Records, 1941-1945
  - News Releases about Stanford (1 of 3) (Box 24, Folder 193)
  - News Releases about Stanford (2 of 3) (Box 24, Folder 194)
  - News Releases about Stanford (3 of 3) (Box 24, Folder 195)
  - 1942 maps catalog prepared by O.S.S. and Military Intelligence (Box 24, Folder 196)
  - Dibble General Hospital – A History (Box 24, Folder 197)
  - American Field Service (Box 24, Folder 198)
  - Civil Affairs Training School (Box 24, Folder 199)
  - Civil Defense (Box 24, Folder 200)
  - Civil Defense, Disaster Preparedness & Relief Plan, Palo Alto Chapter (Box 24, Folder 201)
  - Civil Defense (Box 24, Folder 202)
  - Committee on University Services (Box 25, Folder 203)
  - Engineering Science and Management War Training Program (Box 25, Folder 204)
  - War News (Box 25, Folder 205)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter pertaining to campus war effort, 1941-1945 (Box 25, Folder 206)
  - Dedication-Stanford University-Roll of Honor World War II, 1952 (Box 25, Folder 207)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: General (Box 25, Folder 208)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: A-B (Box 25, Folder 209)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: C-E (Box 25, Folder 210)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: F-H (Box 25, Folder 211)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: I-M (Box 25, Folder 212)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: N-R (Box 25, Folder 213)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: S-T (Box 26, Folder 214)
  - Letters from servicemen to Donald B. Tresidder: U-Z (Box 26, Folder 215)
  - War Memorial, World War II (General Secretary's Office) (Box 26, Folder 216)
  - Letters from Stanford men in service during World War II to Prof.Thomas Barclay (Box 26, Folder 217)
- History of the 4th Stanford Ambulance Unit Written by One of its Members, Series 4
  - Chapters 1-2 (Box 26, Folder 218)
  - Chapters 3-4 (Box 26, Folder 219)
  - Chapter 5 (Box 26, Folder 220)
  - Chapter 6 (Box 26, Folder 221)
  - Chapter 7 (Box 26, Folder 222)
  - Chapters 8-9 (Box 26, Folder 223)
  - Chapter 10 (Box 26, Folder 224)
  - Chapter 11 (Box 26, Folder 225)
  - Chapter 12 (Box 26, Folder 226)
  - Original typescript (Box 27)
    Access to Collection
    Restricted--fragile.
- Additional Materials, Accession ARCH-2009-275
  - War Dead List (Box 1)
- Additional materials, 1919; Accession ARCH-2015-090
  - Camp Fremont lease, 1919 (Box 1)
- Additional Materials, 1943; Accession ARCH-2017-016
  - War Ration Book, Charmian Kolar, circa 1943 (Box 1)